# Ratnadeep Mitra

# **Data Scientist**

Arlington, VA | (202) 515-0174 | r\_mitra20@outlook.com

in linkedin.com/in/ratnadeep-mitra/

**SUMMARY** 

Motivated Data Scientist with a strong background in software development and experience in data processing and machine learning algorithms and dashboard development to create efficient workflows, solve challenging business problems, and deliver valuable insights. Continuous learner and passionate about deep learning, natural language processing, and data visualization.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## **Data Scientist**

July 2019 - Present

## HANOVER RESEARCH - Arlington, VA

- Develop and maintain interactive rankings simulator application for clients to diagnose university rankings and perform real-time simulations to identify the highest improvement metrics. Create D3 visualizations for the user interface and perform ETL operations using R and PostgreSQL.
- Perform text data analysis using **Python**, and was involved in developing code for gibberish detection model for survey responses with over 95% accuracy.
- Performed extensive data wrangling in R to design and build 5 executive dashboards in **Tableau** for discovering industry trends and for performance benchmarking.
- Perform data engineering operations for creating a data warehouse and build data pipelines using Microsoft Azure and Microsoft SQL Server.

#### **Data Scientist Consultant**

Sep 2018 - Jun 2019

#### WORLD BANK - Washington, DC

- Reduced data collection and processing time by over 90% for the UNESCO UIS Data
  Harvesting project by automating the collection and preparation of statistical data and
  metadata using R scripts. This project was part of the World Bank's Sustainable
  Development Goals.
- Responsible for migrating the PovcalNet application from C# to R. Implemented regression
  models and statistical computations, and wrote wrapper functions in R to abstract
  complex calculations.

### Senior Software Engineer

Aug 2013 - Jun 2017

## FIRST AMERICAN (INDIA) - Bengaluru, India

- 1 of 5 employees out of 700+ to win 'Top Performer' award for exceptional performance in 2016 2nd quarter.
- Developed and administrated SQL database to analyze employees' competencies to aid team building and hiring process.
- Contributed software engineering expertise in a client-facing role in the development of web interfaces and APIs.
- Spearheaded project to develop a tool to facilitate cross-selling.
- Mentored fresh graduates joining the organization.

## **EDUCATION**

M.S. in Analytics (Concentration in Data Science) Georgetown University Aug 2017 - May 2019

### **CORE COMPETENCIES**

Data Mining/Processing, Statistical and Predictive Analysis, Machine Learning, Data Visualization, Natural Language Processing

### **TECHNICAL EXPERTISE**

#### Languages:

• R, Python, SQL

#### **Tools and Frameworks:**

• Tableau, AWS, Spark, Hadoop, Keras, Shiny, TensorFlow, MS Azure

#### Others:

 Web UI and API Development, C#, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Agile Scrum

#### CERTIFICATIONS

- Deep Learning Specialization (Coursera, April 2020)
- Data Scientist with R Language (Simplilearn, July 2016)
- Oracle Database SQL Certified Expert (Oracle, July 2013)

## OTHER EXPERIENCE

- Data Science Research Intern for Hanover Research
- Database Specialist for Georgetown Graduate Analytics Program
- Graduate Teaching Assistant for Advanced Programming Topics, Introduction to Information Technology and Data Visualization
- Mentor for Georgetown Graduate
   Analytics Program Fall 2018 cohort
- Speaker at Georgetown Graduate Analytics Student Internship Experience Seminar
- Participated in Deloitte Foundation Core Consulting Series